<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Anu Jain</title>
    <link href="https://anujain.me/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://anujain.me" />
    <updated>2019-02-10T07:55:34-08:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Anu</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://anujain.me</id>

    <entry>
        <title>To Break the Continuity </title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/to-break-the-continuity/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/to-break-the-continuity/</id>
            <category term="The Spell of Stories"/>

        <updated>2019-02-10T07:55:17-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/12/IMG_20190127_162708.jpg" alt="" />
                     Mera desh mahaan, log phir bhi pareshan My country is great,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/12/IMG_20190127_162708.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><img class="post__image" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/12/IMG_20190127_162708.jpg" alt="" width="3987" height="2939"></p>
<p><em>Mera desh mahaan, log phir bhi pareshan</em> <br> My country is great, but the people are still upset/unhappy<br> <br> <em>Dekho, magar sirf pyar se</em><br> You may look at me, but do so only with love<br> <br> <em>Thand rakh, ai bhi pass ho jana hai</em><br> Stay cool, this too will pass<br> <br> <em>Duniya gol hae, phir milenge, ta-ta, bye, bye</em><br> The earth is round, we’ll meet again, ta-ta, bye<br> <br> <em>Rab hi malik hae </em><br> God is the boss<br> <br> The above would evoke a sense of ‘déjà vu’ in anyone who has traversed some roads in India. Such avowals, and plenty more philosophical and comical ones, are painted on auto rickshaws, trucks, and buses throughout the country. Reading these and pondering their relevance to life is a pursuit that helps keep my mind off traffic and pollution.<br> <br> Another very common declaration on auto rickshaws is “<em>Buri nazar wale, tera moonh kala</em>”, which translates to, “To the one with the evil eye, may your face be blackened”. In the Indian culture a face is blackened to insult an individual. However, walking to my hotel in Dehradun I saw a parked auto rickshaw that said-<br> <br> <em>Buri nazar wale, tera bhi bhala ho</em><br> To the one with the evil eye, may you be blessed as well.<br> <br> I stopped. I read the saying again. This was a first for sure! A diminutive smile sprung on my lips. I chuckled. In spite of the blazing sun overhead, I felt a wisp of cool shade find its way to my heart. <br> <br> I went over the auto rickshaw person. “Where to?” he asked, I answered, “I don’t really need to go anywhere, but may I speak with you for a minute?” He looked at me quizzically through his over-sized sun glasses, shifted a bit in his bright red, skin-tight, transparent shirt that showed off his bulging biceps. Then ignoring me, he started digging under his extra-long hot-pink painted pinky with a screw driver. I repeated my question and he shrugged his shoulder nonchalantly; reminding me of my teenager saying, “What ever.”<br> <br> Deciding to get to the point, I asked him, “This saying written on your auto, did you get it painted?” <br> <br> “Yes, why?” he quipped.<br> <br> “I found it very interesting. What made you change the ‘black face’ one to this one?”<br> <br> He laughed. The sun glasses came off. I could see his large black eyes lighten up. “Madam <em>ji</em>, I like breaking things. I broke my parents dream when I dropped out of school. I break a bottle of alcohol every night. I break the hearts of girls in this city. I break the bodies of people who mess with me. This time I decided to break something different- the chain”. <br> <br> I reminded myself to breathe. And asked, “Break which chain <em>ji</em>?” The ‘ji’ tumbled out on its own. I wanted to ensure he felt respected. <br> <br> “The chain of evil eyes, Madam ji. See, if you look at me with an evil eye, and I blacken your face, you will look at me the same way again. The evil will keep coming back to me. Instead if I ask God to bless you; I break the chain of evil eyes and black faces. Better for me too, <em>correct na</em>”, he said it all in one breath. <br> <br> Wow! Could breaking something ever be better?</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Ribbons of Life</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/ribbons-of-life/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/ribbons-of-life/</id>
            <category term="Attempts to Capture Life"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T07:59:32-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/7/IMG_20190127_161711.jpg" alt="" />
                    You on one branch, me on another We leap and hold on&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/7/IMG_20190127_161711.jpg" alt="" />
                <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/7/IMG_20190127_161711-3.52.12-PM.jpg" width="4032" height="3024">
<p>You on one branch, me on another</p>
<p>We leap and hold on to a ribbon</p>
<p>Then together are we?</p>
<p>Up against the blue sky</p>
<p>Connected for eternity.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Little Martians?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/little-martians/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/little-martians/</id>
            <category term="Attempts to Capture Life"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T08:04:14-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/6/IMG_20190113_093929.jpg" alt="" />
                     Light will find its way through the minutest crack, the tiniest dew&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/6/IMG_20190113_093929.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><img class="post__image--center" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/6/IMG_20190113_093929.jpg" width="3583" height="1497"></p>
<p>Light will find its way through</p>
<p>the minutest crack, the tiniest dew</p>
<p>Little Martians poised on my roof?</p>
<p>Or one of life's radiant proof? </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Perfect Moments</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/perfect-moments/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/perfect-moments/</id>
            <category term="Attempts to Capture Life"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T08:07:51-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/1/IMG_20181103_161341-1.jpg" alt="" />
                     Cool shade and sand A friend to enjoy it with Perfect&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/1/IMG_20181103_161341-1.jpg" alt="" />
                <p class="align-left"><img class="post__image" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/1/IMG_20181103_161341-2.jpg" alt="" width="415" height="583"></p>
<p>Cool shade and sand</p>
<p class="align-left">A friend to enjoy it with</p>
<p>Perfect moments</p>
<p>Unbounded happiness</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Expectant Eyes</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/expectant-eyes/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/expectant-eyes/</id>
            <category term="Attempts to Capture Life"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T07:59:19-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/5/MVIMG_20180830_090953.jpg" alt="" />
                    Her scythed hand unearths treasures, and to my expectant presence, oblivious she remains.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/5/MVIMG_20180830_090953.jpg" alt="" />
                <figure class="post__image post__image--center" ><img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/5/MVIMG_20180830_090953.jpg" width="640" height="355">
<figcaption ></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Her scythed hand unearths treasures,</p>
<p>and </p>
<p>to my expectant presence,</p>
<p>oblivious she remains.</p>
<p>Therein lies her beauty,</p>
<p>her humility,</p>
<p>In renderig non-existent</p>
<p> the shroud of a receiver</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Web of Interconnectedness </title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/web-of-interconnectedness/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/web-of-interconnectedness/</id>
            <category term="The Spell of Stories"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T07:59:49-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/4/IMG_20190129_115451.jpg" alt="" />
                    I was robbed, yet I was found. My heart started racing the second I saw my&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/4/IMG_20190129_115451.jpg" alt="" />
                <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/4/IMG_20190129_115451-1.jpg" width="2176" height="1340">
<h4 id="mcetoc_1d2o05ei40">I was robbed, yet I was found. </h4>
<p>My heart started racing the second I saw my backpack’s zip open, and even though I frantically looked through all the pockets, deep inside I knew that my wallet had been stolen. In that moment yesterday, with hundreds of people teeming all around me at the Delhi Metro station, I felt alone... very alone. My personal space violated. My sense of freedom associated with money, gone.<br> <br> I went to the nearest guard/police and narrated my story, but I was handed off from one official to another; with a reprimand, “Aap ko careful rehna chahiye tha madam.” (<em>You should have been careful Madam</em>)<br> <br> By then my mind had started imagining the thief’s identity: a young man, with swift, darting eyes, a sly smile and a self-congratulatory attitude. I was sinking in a swamp of self-pity, asking myself, “What did I ever do to harm this person, why has he placed me in this mess?”<br> <br> I eventually found my way to the Police Control Room dazzling with banks of CCTV screens. For a couple of seconds relief permeated through me, hoping that they would look at the CCTV footage, find the thief and my ordeal would be over. Ah! But reality is usually different! I was told to go to another Police Station to file a FIR, start an investigation and only then would the police start the process of checking the footage. I sank into a broken chair while they told me, “Madam bhool jao, kaun dhoondega chor ko? Aap aage ke liye khyaal rakho ab.” (<em>Madam, forget it, who is going to look for the thief? Just be careful in the future now</em>.)<br> <br> I walked back into the crowds with tears stinging my eyes, uncertain of what to do next, trying to reach Ashim in USA. The weight of all the perceived and real frustrations of living and working in India plummeting on me like a row of dominoes set into motion. Talking to Ashim brought some calm, but anxiety was once again paramount while recollecting the specific credit and debit cards, Indian and US ids in the wallet. While Gautam and Ashim took over the chore of cancelling all the cards, ordering replacements, placing fraud alerts on my accounts; I looked around once again noticing the people oblivious to my tears.<br> <br> I finally sat in the Metro train to head over to Gurgaon. Something about closing my eyes in the moving train allowed me to separate myself from my journey. I realized that my few hours sans the security of my cards and cash, had rendered me a small glimpse into the vulnerability millions of penniless people feel while facing life every day. My hurt at the indifference around me brought to the forefront the many instances, when I might have ignored offering comfort to another being. My families rallying around me guided me towards gratitude for all that I have.<br> <br> And then… I was able to breathe out my self-pity and my anger; take in a few composed breaths and send my love to the ‘swift and sly person’ who stole my wallet and hoped that the money does him good.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Life in Sync ~ Beautiful Moments</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/life-in-sync-beautiful-moments/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/life-in-sync-beautiful-moments/</id>
            <category term="The Spell of Stories"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T08:11:29-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/8/IMG_20180907_113627.jpg" alt="" />
                     A bright blue saree, a large nose pin, orange marigolds in snow-white&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/8/IMG_20180907_113627.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><img class="post__image" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/8/IMG_20180907_113627-1.jpg" alt="" width="3585" height="2658"></p>
<p>A bright blue <em>saree</em>, a large nose pin, orange marigolds in snow-white hair, a bulging shoulder bag and a face that showed every wrinkle of her 70 or so years of age. She was walking bit by bit towards my parked car; my attention divided between the book in my lap, and the people passing by. She stopped and put a hand out to rest against the car’s hood; gently closed her eyes, took a deep breath and wiped the sweat off her forehead with her <em>saree pallu</em>. The sweltry day was taking its toll on her slight frame, and the disproportionately large bag seemed to affect not just her gait, but also her breathing.  <br><br>My heart beat faster with an unknown urgency. She reminded me of a delicate bird, struggling because of the weight someone had clipped on to its wings. Was there a way I could do something, anything, to stretch those wrinkles around her mouth to a smile? But then, had the lady noticed me sitting inside the car, she would not have rested against the hood. Would it be feasible to take away her few moments of respite just to fulfill my desire to help? Would she feel embarrassed, and walk away once I made my presence known? I stilled my body while my mind frantically groped for answers. Would I even be able to communicate with her as we most probably would be unable to converse in a common language? I started looking around to spot my driver, wanting him to ask the lady if we could give her a ride. <br><br>Of course I forgot about the head movement, of course she noticed me, of course her calm expression changed to a cautious one and of course she jerkily moved her hand away from the car. <span id="fullpost">I grabbed the water bottle next to me, smiled, gently opened the door and offered the bottle to her. She looked at me hesitatingly, shook her head with downcast eyes and walked away.<br><br>I was so annoyed with myself. I should have been more careful not to move; instead of lending a hand, I had burst the lady’s miniscule bubble of privacy.   <br><br>I was feeling blue and I saw blue in the car window again. She was back. I opened the door and patted the seat next to me. She sat down, opened her bag and offered me a banana. I took it and offered her the water bottle again. She took it.   <br><br>I ate, she drank; we smiled. She rested for a couple of minutes. Those minutes brought such tranquility to me. She took my head in both her hands, made a small kissing sound in the air, opened the car door and walked away.<br><br>I was trying to help someone in distress. In turn, I became distressed and she kissed my distress away. Our lives were in sync.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Beauty and Trash</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/beauty-and-trash/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/beauty-and-trash/</id>
            <category term="The Spell of Stories"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T08:11:59-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/9/DSC_0509.JPG" alt="" />
                     The stench permeated the car interior. I rolled up my car&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/9/DSC_0509.JPG" alt="" />
                <p><img class="post__image" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/9/DSC_0509-1.JPG" alt="" width="583" height="442"></p>
<p>The stench permeated the car interior. I rolled up my car window the very instant my olfactory senses were aroused to a heightened state. The words ‘shock and awe’ flashed in front of my eyes. With a shrinking nose and expanding frown lines, I looked out the window to track the instigator who had defiled the air. <br> <br> A rickety tractor, which looked like a shantytown house on wheels, was parked ahead to my left. Ripped, dull brown cardboard sagged against its sides creating a makeshift enclosure. Ropes and wires at various places held the jalopy together. This mournful object was imparting the unearthly odor; one could well call, ‘the smell from hell’. Curiosity got the better of my nose, and I peered at the tractor through the window. It was overloaded with mounds of garbage of all sizes, shapes, decaying intensity, colors, etc. I wished my daughter would return from her class soon so we could leave.<br> <br> The article ‘Singapore- The Squeaky Clean City’ in the glossy magazine in my lap was unable to hold my attention any more. I eyed the mangled remains of packaging, vegetables, bottles, paper, plastic Styrofoam, and the likes in the truck. Partially hidden in this pile, I noticed a lady sitting atop the garbage in a corner. She was sorting the garbage into smaller heaps and I could decipher plastics in one section, bottles in another, neatly folded crinkled paper in another. <br> <br> There was a hypnotic quality to the earnestness in her labor. Being surrounded by foul smelling garbage did not mar her beauty. Rather, the dismal surroundings enhanced the exquisiteness of the festive red saree draped seductively and red bangles that slid up and down her arms as she worked. Suddenly she smiled, dug her hands into the pile and pulled out a glittering golden ribbon; a discarded party decoration. She tenderly straightened it out, wound it around her hand, jumped off the tractor, arranged the sparkling trimming around the tractor’s bonnet up front, and took a couple of steps back to view the effect. Her face, resplendent with joy, reminded me of a mother doting on her child. <br> <br> There I was; so disturbed by the stench, yet so enamored by the sight. I fervently felt like adding beauty to this already beautiful lady’s day. I tried talking to her but she spoke Kannada, I spoke Hindi. I saw a flower lady near by and bought some extra long lengths of ‘<em>gajra</em>’ jasmine flowers strung together. Walking over to the star of my day, I offered her the flower string. She graced me with a delightful smile, hesitatingly took the string and immediately arranged it in her long hair. I prayed that the fragrance of the flowers may be powerful enough to prevail over the smell of her surroundings. Sounds like a cliché, but she did prove that a lotus has the ability to rise beyond the dirty water it grows in and maintain its purity and beauty. </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Sensory Overload</title>
        <author>
            <name>Anu</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://anujain.me/sensory-overload/"/>
        <id>https://anujain.me/sensory-overload/</id>
            <category term="The Spell of Stories"/>

        <updated>2019-02-08T08:08:41-08:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/10/MVIMG_20180902_174700-2.jpg" alt="" />
                     Have you ever wished for the ability to close your eyes&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/10/MVIMG_20180902_174700-2.jpg" alt="" />
                <p><img class="post__image" src="https://anujain.me/media/posts/10/MVIMG_20180902_174700-3.jpg" alt="" width="734" height="550"></p>
<p>Have you ever wished for the ability to close your eyes and in effect close your ears as well? The ability to stop the constant cacophony, to hit the mute button on all electronic devices, to zip the lips of people around you, to soundproof your tympanic membrane . . . <br> <br> My recent round trip from Bangalore to Dehradun left me wanting to move to a city where sign-language was the law. The ordeal started with the 6 am airport bus. The radio blared songs. These were interspersed with a very peppy DJ ensuring that the listeners were paying attention and with advertisements of sexy wardrobes capable of changing my life, apartments that could make my home heavenly, grocery store prices that could double my purchasing power. Wow! What else could one ask for? <br> <br> Well, the two fellow travelers behind me ensured that the 1 hour trip thoroughly enlightened me on the architecture of their under-construction houses, how the grills would be hidden to show off the floor to ceiling windows, the balcony door would have a metal plate sandwiched between the wood, the roof-top garden would be waterproofed, the drop down ladder from the attic could be widened so their wives could access the attic as well, etc, etc. <br> <br> The cell phone of my vivacious neighbor to the left had a ring tone of a child wailing on the top of his lungs. I am sure she could win a popularity contest hands-down because her phone rang every 1-2 minutes. Of course, there were at least 7-8 other cell phones with distinct ring tones ringing melodiously at various intervals as well. The gentleman in front of me was ragging a junior at this unearthly hour; telling him how to handle the next client to clinch the contract. I had selected a seat right under the TV screen thinking that I would be able to see straight out the front window of the bus without an onslaught from the movie that was playing. I forgot out of sight does not mean out of ears as well. <br> <br> What amazed me was the ability of my ears to decipher each and every sound byte and feel the assimilated information pounding in my head. Would technology ever advance to a stage where two conversing people would do so at a wave length privy just to them? Where my cell phone ring would be heard by no one but me? Where I could tune in or tune out of the radios dispensing information to the public? Where separations in the acoustic spectrum would ensure that one person’s music does not become another person’s noise?<br> <br> I turned to my co passenger- my daughter, to share my marvelous vision of the future. My voice at varying decibels had no auditory impact on her. With her eyes closed, she certainly was tuned out, at peace, at rest, enjoying. I decided not to intrude upon her reverie. To make my wait for science’s leap towards noise-free living less inaudible, I realized, I just needed to follow my daughter’s route- purchase a set of head-phones and use them. Except that I would do so without a MP3 attached to the other end.</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
